Guide to the John Vaccaro and the Play-House of the Ridiculous Papers MSS 321
Fales Library and Special Collections
John Vaccaro and the Play-House of the Ridiculous Papers
1959-2005
Fales Library and Special Collections
Vaccaro, John
MSS 321
8.25 Linear Feet in 3 records cartons, 5 flat boxes, 4 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, 2 flat file folders, and 1 half manuscript box.
John Vaccaro is an actor and theatrical director who became a primary figure of the Off-Off Broadway and gay theater communities in New York City. The John Vaccaro Papers preserve the items related to Vaccaro's theatrical productions, including scripts, correspondence, photographs, posters and critical notices. Materials date from 1959 to 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Vaccaro, 2011. The accession number associated with this gift is 2011.321.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series. Oversize materials are listed at the end of the finding aid.
Series I: Projects
Series II: Posters and Ephemera
Series III: Photographs
Series IV: Publications
Oversize - Series I: Projects
Oversize - Series II: Posters and Ephemera
Biographical Note
John Vaccaro was born in Steubenville, Ohio on December 6, 1929. After serving in the U.S. Navy from 1951-1955, and receiving a B.A. in English from Ohio State University in 1961, he moved to New York City and became involved in the underground art and film community of the early sixties. After acting in Jack Smith's Normal Love and Flaming Creatures, and performing in the "Happenings" of Robert Whitman and Walter DeMaria, Vaccaro founded the Play-House of the Ridiculous in the summer of 1965. Early collaborators and playwrights in this community included Ronald Tavel, Charles Ludlam and Kenneth Bernard. In 1967, during preparatory work for a production of Ludlam's play Conquest of the Universe, or When Queens Collide Vaccaro and Ludlam came to a disagreement and split into competing companies (Vaccaro retained the Play-House of the Ridiculous; Ludlam founded the Ridiculous Theatrical Company).
Vaccaro's productions were staged at the Coda Gallery, La Mama ETC, the Gotham Art Theater, Max's Kansas City, The American Place Theater, and other Off-Broadway and Off-Off-Broadway venues in New York. In 1970 Vaccaro received a special citation OBIE award. While sometimes performing in and writing the music for his own productions, Vaccaro took his companies on tours of Europe throughout the 1970s and served as director of the Native American Theatrical Ensemble. His theatrical influences include Alfred Jarry, Amiri Baraka, Eugene Ionesco, Charlie Chaplin, Antonin Artaud, and Jack Smith. In addition to the non-professional actors often employed in his productions, Vaccaro is associated with a variety of figures from the New York art and theater worlds, including Taylor Mead, Beverly Grant, Mary Woronov, Rene Ricard, Rosalyn Drexler, Ultra Violet, and Richard Weinstock. Vaccaro has lectured at a number universities and workshops, and has directed performances of his productions for the BBC and Dutch television.
Partial List of Productions (as director)
"Life of Juanita Castro" by Ronald Tavel (1965)
"Shower" by Ronald Tavel (1965)
"The Life of Lady Godiva" by Ronald Tavel (1966)
"Screen Test"/"Indira Gandhi's Daring Device" both by Ronald Tavel (1966)
"Big Hotel" by Charles Ludlam (1967)
"Conquest of the Universe" by Charles Ludlam (1967)
"The Moke Eater" by Kenneth Bernard (1968)
"Monkeys of the Organ Grinder" by Kenneth Bernard (1969)
"Cock Strong" by Tom Murrin (1969)
"Heaven Grand In Amber Orbit" by Jackie Curtis (1969)
"Son of Cock Strong" by Tom Murrin (1970)
"Night Club" by Kenneth Bernard (1970)
"XXXXX" by William M. HOffman (1970)
"Life of Lady Godiva" by Ronald Tavel (1971)
"The Life of Juanita Castro" by Ronald Tavel (1971)
"Persia, A Desert Cheapie" by Bernard Roth & Vaccaro (1972)
"Sissy" by Seth Allen (1972)
"Satyricon" by Paul Foster (1973)
"Elegy for a Down Queen" by Leslie Lee (1973)
"Body Indian" by Hanay Getgoman (1973-1974)
"The Magic Show of Dr. Magico" by Kenneth Bernard (1973-1974)
"La Bohemia" by Vaccaro (1974)
"Workshop of Y.M.C.A." by Gerome Ragni & James Rado (1975-1976)
"The Sixty Minute Queer Show" by Kenneth Bernard (1977)
"Juba" by Lawrence Holder (1978)
"Gulliver's Travels" by William M. Hoffman (1978)
"The Book of Etiquette" by William M. Hoffman (1979)
"The Writer's Opera" by Rosalyn Drexler (1979)
"Derby" by Barry Arnold (1979)
"Vulgar Lives" by Rosalyn Drexler (1979)
"Graven Image" by Rosalyn Drexler (1980)
"Flop" by Seth Allen (1980)
"A Midsummer Night's Dream" by William Shakespeare (1980)
"Starburn" by Rosalyn Drexler (1983)
"La Fin du Cirque" by Kenneth Bernard (1984)
"Transients Welcome" by Rosalyn Drexler (1984-1985)
"Goatman" by Raymond Schanz (1986)
"The Heart That Eats Itself" by Rosalyn Drexler (1987)
"Cara Pina" by Rosalyn Drexler (1992)
Scope and Contents
The John Vaccaro and the Play-House of the Ridiculous Papers contain materials that document Vaccaro's professional theatrical career, ranging from the early 1960s through 2005. The collection preserves Vaccaro's primarily collaborative work, including scripts, notebooks, articles, essays, and correspondence that date back to his early career as an actor in the emerging world of Off-Off Broadway theater in New York. Elements include source material for his productions as well as promotional material in the form of ephemera, flyers, festival programs, posters and postcards. This body of components also includes the work of collaborating playwrights, and material related to the theatrical and Greenwich Village communities of the 1960s, 70s and 80s. In addition, this collection includes professional and personal correspondence, production and personal photography, original illustrations, publications, and a scrapbook. Materials date from 1959 to 2005.
Experimental theater -- New York (State) -- New York.; Off Off-Broadway theater.; Off-Broadway theater.; Downtown Collection.; Plays (performed works).; Playwriting.; Theatrical producers and directors.; Actors.; Vaccaro, John; Bernard, Kenneth; Drexler, Rosalyn; Ludlam, Charles; Tavel, Ronald; La Mama Experimental Theatre Club; Play-House of the Ridiculous
- Series I: Projects, 1959-1992; 2.75 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 half manuscript box.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Projects contains the work of John Vaccaro and others. Materials inculde press clippings, screenplays, contracts, and ephemera generally related to the titular project. Materials date from 1959 to 1992.
  Arrangement
  Series I: Projects is organized alphabetically by project title.
  - American Indians N.A.T.E., 1973; 9 media elements (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "American Indians (Niagara Falls)", 1973, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Article About Cino etc.", Undated; 29 media elements (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Big Hotel, 1967; 10 media elements (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Ludlam, Charles -- History-Sources
  - Body Indian I and II, Undated; 3 media elements (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Book of Etiquette", 1986; 16 media elements (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cara Pina Script, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cockstrong, 1971; 73 media elements (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Colleges (Lectures)", Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conquest of the Universe Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Conquest of the Universe Contract, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Conquest of the Universe 1 of 2, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conquest of the Universe 2 of 2, 1967, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Derby Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Derby, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Destruction of Atlantis Rehersal, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Magico, 1973, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Etiquette Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Etiquette Revival, 1978, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Evergreen Review, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Flop, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Flop Script, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Goatman, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Goatman Script, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Graven Image Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Graven Image, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Gulliver's Travels Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gulliver's Travels, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Heart That Eats Itself, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - The Heart That Eats Itself Script, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Heaven Grand 1 of 2, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Heaven Grand 2 of 2, 1969 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Heaven Grand Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - "Indira Gandhi", 1966, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Indira Gandhi's Daring Device Script, 1965, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Juba, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Juba Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - La Bohemia, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Lady Godiva Contract, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - La Fin Du Cirque Script, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - La Fin Du Cirque, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - La Justice Script, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Le Justice", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Life of Lady Godiva, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959 - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Moke-Eater, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Moke-Eater Script, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Monkeys of the Organ Grinder, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The New Yorker, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Night Club Script, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Night Club, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Nutcracker, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Persia 1 of 2, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Persia 2 of 2, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Persia Notebook, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Pineapple Face, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Play With an Ending, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Play With an Ending Script, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Primitive World, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Primitive World Script, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Room 17C Script, 1983, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rosalyn Drexler, 2003-2004 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Satyricon, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Screen Test/Juanita Castro/Screen Test II", 1965, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Shower/Juanita Castro", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sissy Script, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sissy, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Sixty Minute Queer Show, 1977, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Sixty Minute Queer Show Script, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Son of Cockstrong Script, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Son of Cockstrong, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Songs from Cockstrong, Heaven Grand, Son of Cockstrong", Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Spiders, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Starburn, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Starburn Script, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Theater, Winter 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Theatre in Poland, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Three Plays at New Theatre by K. Bernard", 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Torino Festival, 1991 - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Transients Welcome, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Vulgar Lives, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Vulgar Lives Script, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Writer's Opera, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Writer's Opera Script 1 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Writer's Opera Script 2 of 2, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "XX XXX", 1970 - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series II: Posters and Ephemera, 1981-2005; 1 Linear Feet in 3 flat boxes and 1 half manuscript box.
  Series II: Posters and Ephemera contains posters, publicity material, objects, and a scrapbook. All the materials relate to Vaccaro's theatrical productions and his work with with the Play-House of the Ridiculous. Materials date from 1981 to 2005.
  Series II: Posters and Ephemera is organized alphabetically by production title or the name of the institution.
  - Big Hotel Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Etiquette Posters, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Goodie Pamphlet, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Heart That Eats Itself, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Indira Gandhi/Screen Test Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Indira Gandhi Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Kenneth Bernard "American Drama" article, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Lady Godiva Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Life of Lady Godiva Poster (alternate), Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - La Fin Du Cirque, Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - A Matter of Life and Death, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Moke-Eater Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Nightclub Posters, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - No President Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Otto Award, 2002 (Box 5)
  - Play-House of the Ridiculous Embosser, undated (Box 5)
  - Play-House of the Ridiculous Stamp, undated (Box 5)
  - Play-House of the Ridiculous Repertory Club Membership Cards, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sharon Thompson Piece, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Untitled Double-Sided Sketch, Undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Young American Beatnicks Poster, Undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Series III: Photographs, undated; 1.5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 2 flat boxes.
  Series III: Photographs contains photographs, contact sheets, negatives, and slides pertaining to Vaccaro's productions and personal collection. Most of the people and plays in the photographs in the collection are unidentified at this time. Materials are undated.
  Series III: Photographs has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from Vaccaro.
  - Daniel Nagrin, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs (unsorted), Undated (Box 6, Folder 2-11)
  - Photographs (unsorted), Undated (Box 7A, Folder 1-4)
  - Fred Ohrenstein Photo of John Vaccaro, Undated (Box 7B, Folder 1)
  - Starburn Photos (1 of 2), Undated (Box 7B, Folder 2)
  - Starburn Photos 2 of 2, Undated (Box 7B, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (unsorted), Undated (Box 7B, Folder 4-7)
  - Photographs (unsorted), undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Publications, 1964-2005; 2 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 flat box.
  Series IV: Publications contains monographs, exhibition catalogs, journals, and magazines. The publications were collected by John Vaccaro and are related to theater and music. Some of the publications contain articles about Vaccarro and his work. Materials date from 1964 to 2005. Most of the publications are in English, with a few in French, German, Italian, and Dutch.
  Series IV: Publications has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
  - Publications (Box 11, Folder 9, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Folder 1-14)
- Oversize - Series I: Projects, 1966-1985; 0.5 Linear Feet in 1 oversize flat box.
  Oversize Series I: Projects contains oversize material related to theatrical productions. Materials date from 1966 to 1985.
  Oversize Series I: Projects is arranged alphabetically.
  - "American Indians N.A.T.E.", 1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "American Indians (Niagara Falls)", 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Cockstrong, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Conquest of the Universe, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Magico, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Goatman, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Heaven Grand, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "Indira Gandhi", 1966. 1967 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Juba, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - The Life of Lady Godiva [newspapers], 1969 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous [more newspapers], 1969 - 1976 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Satyricon, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Sissy, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - The Sixty Minute Queer Show, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "XX XXX", Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Oversize - Series II: Posters and Ephemera, 1961-1979; 0.5 Linear Feet in 2 oversize flat boxes and 2 flat file folders.
  Oversize Series II: Posters and Ephemera contains posters and publicity material related to Vaccaro's theatrical productions. Materials date from 1961 to 1979.
  Oversize Series II: Posters and Ephemera is arranged alphabetically.
  - Cockstrong de Tom Murrin Poster, undated (Folder 5)
  - The Derby, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Graven Image Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Gulliver's Travels Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Juba Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - La Bohemia Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Lady Cockstrong" Drawing, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - La Justice Poster, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - La Fin Du Cirque Character Drawings, Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - La Mama Posters, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - A Midsummer Night's Dream Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Persia" (A Desert Cheapie) Posters, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - "Pugliese" Drawing, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - The Sixty Minute Queer Show Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - The Sixty Minute Queer Show Poster (Dutch), 1977, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Theater Im Reichskabarett Poster, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Untitled Stage Sketch, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Vulgar Lives Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Vulgar Lives Poster (alternate), Undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - "WELL LOVE WILL EAT THE WORLD WILL BE PEACEFUL WILL EAT SHIT" Drawing, October 1969 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - The Writer's Opera Poster, Undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - The Life of Lady Godiva, the Playhouse of Ridiculous, Undated (Folder 14, Object 321.2.0001)
    General
    Poster painted on wood.